<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Adrin Jalali - ethics</title><link href="https://adrin.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://adrin.info/feeds/ethics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://adrin.info/</id><updated>2020-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>How we form beliefs, and implications on our beliefs regarding #metoo</title><link href="https://adrin.info/how-we-form-beliefs-and-implications-on-our-beliefs-regarding-metoo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2020-01-15:/how-we-form-beliefs-and-implications-on-our-beliefs-regarding-metoo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="celestekiss" src="files/img/202001-celestekidd-neurips.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a repost of what I posted on
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adrinjalali/status/1217434403044876288"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At NeurIPS @celestekidd gave a keynote on how people form their beliefs. It was
amazing, and had two plot twists which made the audience stand and clap at the
end; something you don&amp;#8217;t see often in academic conferences. Here …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="celestekiss" src="files/img/202001-celestekidd-neurips.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a repost of what I posted on
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adrinjalali/status/1217434403044876288"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At NeurIPS @celestekidd gave a keynote on how people form their beliefs. It was
amazing, and had two plot twists which made the audience stand and clap at the
end; something you don&amp;#8217;t see often in academic conferences. Here&amp;#8217;s a summary,
and I love how it&amp;nbsp;ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1/ Humans continuously form beliefs. These beliefs are constantly updated. In a
sense, our beliefs are probabilistic expectations which directly influence what
we&amp;#8217;re interested&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things which cause a very low, or a very high surprise level, are usually not
interesting to&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, there&amp;#8217;s a low chance that I&amp;#8217;d enjoy a book teaching the English
alphabet, or a book in a language I don&amp;#8217;t understand, and is in an alphabet I
don&amp;#8217;t know, and a topic I&amp;#8217;m not familiar with. In theory I could learn all
those things at the same time, but most probably&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2/ Certainty diminishes interest: you&amp;#8217;re not curious about things you think you
know. Which makes sense and is reasonable; the issue is when people are certain
about certain issues when they shouldn&amp;#8217;t be. Anybody who&amp;#8217;s discussed politics
with extended family is familiar with&amp;nbsp;this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research shows it&amp;#8217;s what we think we know defines what we&amp;#8217;re interested in, and
not what we actually know. Worse: we&amp;#8217;re more inclined to reject a correct
feedback if we think we already know the [wrong] answer. but why do we have
those wrong&amp;nbsp;beliefs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/ Certainty is driven by feedback. At least when it comes to high level
beliefs such as concepts. If there&amp;#8217;s no feedback to correct people&amp;#8217;s beliefs,
they may form one w/o proper evidence. If a belief results in correct answers
even if it&amp;#8217;s not justified, it&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;reinforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means: if we have a belief, and we look for material online and the first
video we see agrees with that belief, it&amp;#8217;s reinforced, and that will make us be
interested in material which agree with what we now believe in, even if that
first video was factually&amp;nbsp;wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4/ Less feedback may encourage&amp;nbsp;overconfidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have different ideas of the same concept, let it be &amp;#8220;Joe Biden&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;a
cup&amp;#8221;, even in the same&amp;nbsp;context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, people tend to over estimate how many other people share their
understanding of the same&amp;nbsp;concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/ Humans form beliefs&amp;nbsp;quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early evidence matters more than later&amp;nbsp;evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, when it comes to &amp;#8220;activated charcoal&amp;#8221;, people go from &amp;#8220;unsure&amp;#8221; to
&amp;#8220;certain it has health benefits&amp;#8221; in two or three clicks and a few very short&amp;nbsp;videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we get to the interesting&amp;nbsp;conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s no such thing as a neutral tech platform: not Facebook, not Google, not
anyone else. Any platform showing content to users, sorts and filters content
for them resulting in forming different beliefs in different&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimizing for engagement on these platforms means we&amp;#8217;re trying to keep users
on a given platform for longer, and that&amp;#8217;s through showing them what they
enjoy, which means enforcing what people already believe in and are interested
in, rather than changing or correcting&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that is to say algorithms pushing content online have profound impact on
what we believe, which result in us making decisions, and not benign ones. With
a few clicks we may walk away being convinced that we shouldn&amp;#8217;t vaccinate our
kid, or that climate change is not&amp;nbsp;real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part: it may seem to be a scary time to be a man in tech right now.
Many men have anxiety about how to talk about gender, and how to interact with
women post #metoo. There&amp;#8217;s a sense that careers may be destroyed over awkward
passes or&amp;nbsp;misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People do believe that men are being fired for subtle comments or minor jokes.
And this perception rightfully makes people&amp;nbsp;nervous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is that this perception is not correct, and understanding how we form
beliefs, this is&amp;nbsp;why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that it takes an immense amount of mistreatment for most women to
actually complain, due to the fact that most complaints result in retaliation
and law suits cost so much money and time that most people cannot&amp;nbsp;afford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This prior should tell us that if we hear about a case, some unusually bad
behavior has happened. But why do we believe a minor&amp;nbsp;misconduct?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;when a harassment case becomes public, offenders almost universally apologize
for a minor fraction of the&amp;nbsp;offense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes people believe that they&amp;#8217;re often being prosecuted for a minor
mistreatment, and makes those reportings seem unreasonable or even&amp;nbsp;unethical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unfair to men who are anxious and women who miss out on those
professional&amp;nbsp;interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, 3&amp;nbsp;takes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1/ if you hear about a woman complaining around you, she&amp;#8217;s probably been
through much more than you&amp;#8217;re aware&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you hear about a woman having issues, chances are they&amp;#8217;re having more issues
and that&amp;#8217;s the time to ask questions and help&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2/ when you hear a man apologizing for a misunderstanding, you should know it&amp;#8217;s
a standard response and completely predictable, no matter what happened from
sexual harassment to sexual assault, and that they&amp;#8217;re not apologizing for all
their&amp;nbsp;misconducts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/ unless men are deeply doing wrong by women around them, they&amp;#8217;re with very
rare exceptions, incredibly&amp;nbsp;safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;#8217;t fear being attacked for minor comments or misunderstandings,
cause that&amp;#8217;s not what&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s [false] myth propagated by harassers and&amp;nbsp;offenders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the link for the full video: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6qIodcz8o-Q"&gt;&lt;img alt="Celeste Kidd - NeurIPS 2019 - How to
Know" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/6qIodcz8o-Q/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ethics"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="machine-learning"></category></entry><entry><title>A Criticism of “Detecting Sexual Orientation Using Neural Networks”</title><link href="https://adrin.info/a-criticism-of-detecting-sexual-orientation-using-neural-networks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2017-10-05:/a-criticism-of-detecting-sexual-orientation-using-neural-networks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d like to talk about this study: &lt;a href="https://osf.io/fk3xr/"&gt;Deep neural networks are more accurate than humans at detecting sexual orientation from facial images&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s not going to be a praise of the&amp;nbsp;research!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="damaging-message"&gt;Damaging&amp;nbsp;Message&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put this study in the same category as studies trying to argue …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d like to talk about this study: &lt;a href="https://osf.io/fk3xr/"&gt;Deep neural networks are more accurate than humans at detecting sexual orientation from facial images&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s not going to be a praise of the&amp;nbsp;research!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="damaging-message"&gt;Damaging&amp;nbsp;Message&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put this study in the same category as studies trying to argue women are different than men, usually in derogatory ways, e.g. proving they&amp;#8217;re weaker, less intelligent, or worse at math. Recently we had the google engineer citing a whole bunch of them to support his argument about why men are better coders, or men are better in tech, or whatever bullshit he wanted to argue for. Honestly I won&amp;#8217;t bother reading it; I mostly heard about it in podcasts and read about it in the news. My point is, those gender related studies tend to be more damaging than beneficial, and I see no point in doing them. I understand this is a very consequentialist way of assessing the value of the work, but I&amp;#8217;m comfortable with it for&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s the same with the study in question. What&amp;#8217;s the point of having a module predicting people&amp;#8217;s sexual orientation given a face image, other than some other people using it in an argument such as: &amp;#8220;Your face shouts you&amp;#8217;re gay, scientifically proven&amp;#8221;!!! I&amp;#8217;m sure our dear homophobes out there can think of more damaging ways of using the results of this research. This is all I could come up&amp;nbsp;with!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="methodology"&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t even know where to start. I&amp;#8217;ll split these points into the ones questioning the validity of the study, and the ones which are simply poor&amp;nbsp;wording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="questioning-validity"&gt;Questioning&amp;nbsp;Validity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="auc-calculation"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;calculation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a classification problem, you&amp;#8217;d use your module to predict the outcome, draw the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt;, and calculate the Area Under &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROC&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt;). Pretty straightforward for a binary classification, which is the case in this paper. What I don&amp;#8217;t understand, is this randomly choosing a straight person&amp;#8217;s photo to compare against a homosexual, to calculate an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt;. I simply don&amp;#8217;t understand why you&amp;#8217;d do that, and as a result, I can&amp;#8217;t assess the performance measures reported in the&amp;nbsp;article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="variance-of-the-accuracy"&gt;Variance of the&amp;nbsp;accuracy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They report one &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt; performance for those 20 folds. I guess the results are accumulated over 20 folds and one single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt; is calculated overall. This is important, because the calculated performance usually highly depends on the random split of the data. Therefore without a data showing the distribution of the calculated AUCs, one single number is not representative of how reliable the model in reality&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="svd-on-each-fold-separately-or-not"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVD&lt;/span&gt; on each fold separately or&amp;nbsp;not?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any data analysis, it is crucial to apply [virtually all] preprocessing steps only on the training data. Otherwise you&amp;#8217;re already seeing the test data before even starting you training, and that&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is not clear weather they run a separate &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVD&lt;/span&gt; for each of those 20 folds they have or not. If they do &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVD&lt;/span&gt; once and use the same features on all those folds, the results are immediately invalid. I cannot tell from the text what they&amp;#8217;ve done, and I couldn&amp;#8217;t see a link to their source code. My guess is that they are actually doing it the right way, but it&amp;#8217;s not written&amp;nbsp;clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="model-interpretation"&gt;Model&amp;nbsp;Interpretation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoting the&amp;nbsp;article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gender atypicality of gay faces extended beyond morphology. Gay men had less facial hair, suggesting differences in androgenic hair growth, grooming style, or both. They also had lighter skin, suggesting potential differences in grooming, sun exposure, and/or testosterone levels. Lesbians tended to use less eye makeup, had darker hair, and wore less revealing clothes (note the higher neckline), indicating less gender-typical grooming and style. Furthermore, although women tend to smile more in general (Halberstadt, Hayes, &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Pike, 1988), lesbians smiled less than their heterosexual counterparts. Additionally, consistent with the association between baseball caps and masculinity in American culture (Skerski, 2011), heterosexual men and lesbians tended to wear baseball caps (see the shadow on their foreheads; this was also confirmed by a manual inspection of individual images). The gender atypicality of the faces of gay men and lesbians is further explored in Study&amp;nbsp;2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing these factors with the reported &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AUC&lt;/span&gt;, you could argue that social trends and stereotypes followed by many people, has a substantial factor in giving the classifier its power. To better understand my point, assume you want to train a classifier predicting whether or not a person in a picture is a transgender. Since many transgender people follow an exaggerated version of the opposite gender&amp;#8217;s stereotypes in the society, and the skull itself is predictive of the sex of the person to a good extent on its own, the model would probably have an easy time giving the right&amp;nbsp;outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GHl8xvc-GCI"&gt;&lt;img alt="Skull and sex" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/GHl8xvc-GCI/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean, is that if you have a model which doesn&amp;#8217;t take into account the confound social variables to predict a certain variable, your results are&amp;nbsp;crap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="poor-wording"&gt;Poor&amp;nbsp;wording&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="not-a-deep-neural-network-dnn-method"&gt;Not a Deep Neural Network (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNN&lt;/span&gt;)&amp;nbsp;Method&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article suggests DNNs can achieve the reported performance, while using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNN&lt;/span&gt; only to extract features, and then feeding them to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVD&lt;/span&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt;-&amp;gt;logistic regression pipeline. How is that a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNN&lt;/span&gt; method? I can only imagine they&amp;#8217;ve chosen to advertise it as such, due to the hype around deep learning; after all, who would dare to argue with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNN&lt;/span&gt; these days? Basically, the statement &amp;#8220;deep neural networks can detect sexual orientation from faces&amp;#8221; is a complete misrepresentation of the&amp;nbsp;research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="lasso-and-alpha"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt; and&amp;nbsp;alpha&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say they use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt; with alpha=1 for feature selection. The alpha they refer to is a parameter of elastic net, not &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt;, which results in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt; when set to 1. In other words, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ALWAYS&lt;/span&gt; has that alpha equal to 1, otherwise it&amp;#8217;s not a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LASSO&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="final-remarks"&gt;Final&amp;nbsp;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess at the writing of this post, the article has not been accepted and it may be subject to many changes; in which case, I hope reviewers find the problems I found and many more, so that the final version of the article is a much better work than what I read. But even then, I have a hard time understanding the reason behind such studies. I&amp;#8217;m sure there are much better and more beneficial ways of analyzing the same data and coming up with much better&amp;nbsp;conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I could only analyze this research in depth only if I had the code and the data publicly available. One may argue that I can contact the authors asking for the code and the data; but that&amp;#8217;s not what I call &amp;#8220;publicly&amp;nbsp;available&amp;#8221;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ethics"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="machine-learning"></category></entry><entry><title>On the ethics of CRISPR</title><link href="https://adrin.info/on-the-ethics-of-crispr.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2015-09-01:/on-the-ethics-of-crispr.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Taken from http://www.economist.com/news/leaders/21661651-new-technique-manipulating-genes-holds-great-promisebut-rules-are-needed-govern-its" src="/files/img/economist-editing-humanity.jpg" title="Credits: Economist"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;a href="http://www.economist.com/news/leaders/21661651-new-technique-manipulating-genes-holds-great-promisebut-rules-are-needed-govern-its"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on the ethics of editing human genome and I realized there&amp;#8217;s a missing point in&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRISPR"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRISPR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in short is a technology that allows us to edit our own genome. Of course it has countless number of useful applications as it&amp;#8217;s very simply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Taken from http://www.economist.com/news/leaders/21661651-new-technique-manipulating-genes-holds-great-promisebut-rules-are-needed-govern-its" src="/files/img/economist-editing-humanity.jpg" title="Credits: Economist"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;a href="http://www.economist.com/news/leaders/21661651-new-technique-manipulating-genes-holds-great-promisebut-rules-are-needed-govern-its"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on the ethics of editing human genome and I realized there&amp;#8217;s a missing point in&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRISPR"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRISPR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in short is a technology that allows us to edit our own genome. Of course it has countless number of useful applications as it&amp;#8217;s very simply depicted in the above picture (credit: economist). But recently Chinese scientists have genetically modified human embryos (&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/chinese-scientists-genetically-modify-human-embryos-1.17378"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). Fortunately there&amp;#8217;s been some discussion going on in the community about the ethics of editing human embryo&amp;#8217;s genome, or in general human&amp;nbsp;genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question I want people to think about is: who should/will have access to this technology? Obviously this technology will be very expensive when it reaches the market. Does it mean only rich people will be able to use it? And I&amp;#8217;m not talking about the applications which concern diseases; I&amp;#8217;m rather talking about editing your child&amp;#8217;s genome, to make it smarter, or stronger, or whatever you feel like&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already have too much of a difference between classes in our society. This difference has been empowered partially, if not mostly, by the fact that people have been able to accumulate wealth through time and even generations. If we allow them to be the ones benefiting a technology like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRISPR&lt;/span&gt;, we will practically give them the power to annihilate the lower classes through&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One piece of good news is that some people are talking about how to regulate this sort of technology (&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/regulate-gene-editing-in-wild-animals-1.17523"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). I believe we should start a conversation about who should have access to the technology. This concern is regardless of how and what we decide about the ethics of the method for different applications. If we, as human species, decide not to use it at all, then nobody has access to it. But if we give it a go, then we should make sure all classes of the society have equal access to it. The least and the last we need is to have a rich sub-population with higher physical and mental&amp;nbsp;capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDIT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Thanks to Ian Sample, found a podcast by the guardian &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/audio/2015/may/01/genetics"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ethics"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="genome"></category></entry></feed>