<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Adrin Jalali - open-source</title><link href="https://adrin.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://adrin.info/feeds/open-source.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://adrin.info/</id><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>GIT/GITHUB, how to contribute to an open source project on GitHub?</title><link href="https://adrin.info/gitgithub-how-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project-on-github.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2020-05-28:/gitgithub-how-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project-on-github.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/20190216-git-github.png" title="Credit: https://medium.com/cs-note/git-and-github-for-beginners-i-tutorial-263caa01f9c3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind this post is not to show how to install the tools you need, or
to list a bunch of [at a first glance seemingly random] &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; commands. There
are enough tutorials and blog posts explaining them out there in the wild that
with a web search you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/20190216-git-github.png" title="Credit: https://medium.com/cs-note/git-and-github-for-beginners-i-tutorial-263caa01f9c3"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind this post is not to show how to install the tools you need, or
to list a bunch of [at a first glance seemingly random] &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; commands. There
are enough tutorials and blog posts explaining them out there in the wild that
with a web search you&amp;#8217;ll find too many of them&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goal of this post is to give you the ingredients you need, to contribute
to a project on the GitHub platform and collaborate with other people&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first important point is the distinction between &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;!
GitHub is a platform which uses &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, but it&amp;#8217;s also not the only platform that
uses it. Another somewhat similar platform is &lt;strong&gt;GitLab&lt;/strong&gt;, but there are crucial
differences between the two that has made GitHub a much more convenient place
for a community of strangers to work together. By far the best source of
information I can recommend is the &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2"&gt;Pro Git
book&lt;/a&gt;. To keep it practical, I may not strictly
stick to the definitions present in the book; the idea is to get you started
first, then you can cover the concepts more &lt;em&gt;accurately&lt;/em&gt; once you have more&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; is a version control system, which&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version control is a system that records changes to a file or set of files
over time so that you can recall specific versions later&lt;sup id="fnref:f1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:f1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, to develop a package using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; there is no need for any
server or a platform. Most &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; related tasks you&amp;#8217;d be doing are done
completely locally on your own machine&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issue at the beginning when you start to work with &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; is all the
jargon used around it. To get an idea of what we&amp;#8217;re talking about here, the
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3a2x1iJFJWc"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIT&lt;/span&gt; Workflow - Georgia Tech - Software Development
Process&lt;/a&gt; short video is a great
place to&amp;nbsp;start:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3a2x1iJFJWc" title="GIT Workflow - Georgia Tech - Software Development Process"&gt;&lt;img alt="GIT Workflow - Georgia Tech - Software Development
Process" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/3a2x1iJFJWc/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;#8217;s go through some of the concepts you&amp;#8217;d encounter in
almost any project. For the rest of this post, I&amp;#8217;ll be assuming you&amp;#8217;ve
installed &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; and gone through &lt;a href="https://medium.com/cs-note/git-and-github-for-beginners-i-tutorial-263caa01f9c3"&gt;this
tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
up to Step 3: setup &amp;#8220;config&amp;#8221;, and know your way around a &lt;em&gt;shell/terminal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source tree&lt;/em&gt; is your project&amp;#8217;s folder, with all its subfolders and files that
are included in the project. Using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; you&amp;#8217;ll be keeping track of all the
changes on the source&amp;nbsp;tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are always files and folders which you don&amp;#8217;t want to keep track
of, for instance the &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; directory which keeps compiled binary files of
your project. Cache and temporary files are also another category of files you
would like to exclude from being tracked. The way you tell &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; to ignore
those is through a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file usually put in the root of the project&amp;#8217;s
folder. For most programming languages, there are descent &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;
templates, for instance you can take a look at the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/github/gitignore/blob/master/Python.gitignore"&gt;Python.gitignore&lt;/a&gt;.
This means &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; will not automatically start tracking any of the files and/or
folders mentioned in &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;, but you can still explicitly tell it to do
so if you wish for a particular file or folder. For instance, you may want to
ignore all &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; files, but keep a single &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; in your repository for some
reason. You would be able to do so by explicitly telling &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; to keep track of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start tracking changes to your project&amp;#8217;s source tree using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, you
have a &lt;em&gt;git repository&lt;/em&gt;. The git repository includes all the history of the
whole project in a &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; folder under the root of the project. It&amp;#8217;s worth
noting that by default, every file and folder starting with a dot (&lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;) is a
&lt;em&gt;hidden&lt;/em&gt; file/folder under&amp;nbsp;linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post, I&amp;#8217;ll be using the screenshots taken at the time of
writing the post. It may slightly change through time as GitHub continues its&amp;nbsp;development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of this tutorial, I&amp;#8217;ve setup an example repository on GitHub,
which you can see under &lt;a href="https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo"&gt;this
link&lt;/a&gt;. At first it&amp;#8217;s almost
empty and it looks like&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/initial-orig.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to notice here&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a &lt;em&gt;Watch/Unwatch&lt;/em&gt; button which takes a few states, and you can use it
  to set the amount of notification you&amp;#8217;d be receiving for the repository. You
  will receive a notification (depending on your settings, it can be an email)
  for each event happening on the repository. If you&amp;#8217;d like to be informed and
  notified of every single post and contribution on the repo, then you&amp;#8217;d want
  to &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;watch&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; it. For a busy repository like &lt;em&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/em&gt;, it can be tens of
  emails a day. By default, you&amp;#8217;ll be notified if there&amp;#8217;s a response to the
  issues and pull requests you&amp;#8217;ve been working on (we&amp;#8217;ll get to them&amp;nbsp;shortly).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you like to make the contributors and maintainers of the repository happy,
  you should consider &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Star&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;ing the&amp;nbsp;repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other option up there, is &lt;strong&gt;fork&lt;/strong&gt;, which requires a bit of an explanation.
When you have a git repository, you can &lt;strong&gt;clone&lt;/strong&gt; that by copying everything
you have on that repo, including the &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; folder. So copying is the simplest
type of clone you can have. The clone is the same as the original repository,
including its history (since you copied the &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; folder as well). But let say
you want to clone a repository from a server, and every now and then sync your
local copy with what you have on the server. That&amp;#8217;s why you also have a &amp;#8220;clone
or download&amp;#8221; button on your repository, which gives you the address of the
repository which you can use locally to clone using a &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; command. Here&amp;#8217;s how
you could get the address on the original&amp;nbsp;repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/git-clone-orig.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then you&amp;#8217;d be using the following command to clone that repository&amp;nbsp;locally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git clone https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above command will download the repository and put it in a folder named the
same as the repo itself (&lt;code&gt;example-repo&lt;/code&gt; in this case). At the same time, it
will store the information about from where it got the repository, which is
called a &lt;strong&gt;remote&lt;/strong&gt;, and by default this remote is called &lt;em&gt;origin&lt;/em&gt;. You can get
a list of your remotes using the following command (after going to your repo&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;folder):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; example-repo
$ git remote -v
origin  https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;fetch&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
origin  https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;push&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Again, please note that the above command and all the ones from this point
should be run when you&amp;#8217;re already in your repository&amp;#8217;s folder. As you can see,
there are two identical addressed for two purposes, &lt;em&gt;fetch&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;push&lt;/em&gt;. You can
&lt;em&gt;fetch&lt;/em&gt; changes on the repository which have happened on the &lt;em&gt;remote&lt;/em&gt; server,
but you don&amp;#8217;t have, using &lt;code&gt;git fetch&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;push&lt;/em&gt; any changes on your local
machine using &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;. But there are a few steps before we can do&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that we cloned the repository, without telling a
maintainer of the original repo that we&amp;#8217;re doing so. That&amp;#8217;s because the repo is
a &lt;em&gt;public repository&lt;/em&gt;. For a &lt;em&gt;private repository&lt;/em&gt; you need to be given explicit
permissions by a maintainer/package developer before you can access it.
Basically if you see a repository on GitHub, you can clone&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since you&amp;#8217;re not given explicit permissions, you cannot modify
anything on the original repo, and that also means you cannot do a &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;
directly to it. That&amp;#8217;s why you need to &lt;strong&gt;fork&lt;/strong&gt; the repository before cloning
it. It&amp;#8217;ll create a server side clone of the repo in your account. You can do
that by simply pushing the &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;fork&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; button up there. Please note that if you&amp;#8217;re
a member of one or more organizations, it&amp;#8217;ll ask you to choose an organization
where it should create the fork. Your username will be listed there and you
can choose that to create the fork under your own user and not touch any of the
organizations you&amp;#8217;re a member of. Otherwise it&amp;#8217;ll simply create the fork under
your username. This is what you&amp;#8217;ll see once you fork the&amp;nbsp;repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/initial-fork.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it also tells you from where you forked the repository. Now you
have administrative access to this repository, and that&amp;#8217;s why you also see a
&amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Settings&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; tab. Now if you try to get the clone address of this repo, it
shows you the one you own. Now you have two options, you can delete what you
had cloned, and clone a new one using the new address, which in my case would&amp;nbsp;be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git clone https://github.com/adrinjalali/example-repo.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note that the &lt;code&gt;github-tutorials&lt;/code&gt; is changed to &lt;code&gt;adrinjalali&lt;/code&gt;, my
username. But you can also manipulate your remotes and change what you have to
the new remote address, and avoid having to delete and redownload the
repository. By convention/default, &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; is the remote you own and you sync
your local copy with, and &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt; is the original repository you forked.
Every now and then you&amp;#8217;ll be needing to resync your repository with the changes
which have happened on &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt;, to keep up with the latest changes. So,
let&amp;#8217;s first rename &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git remote rename origin upstream
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then add the new &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git remote add origin https://github.com/adrinjalali/example-repo.git
$ git remote -v
origin  https://github.com/adrinjalali/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;fetch&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
origin  https://github.com/adrinjalali/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;push&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
upstream    https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;fetch&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
upstream    https://github.com/github-tutorials/example-repo.git &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;push&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you had first forked and then cloned your own repo, you&amp;#8217;d need to only add
the &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt; as a remote, and now you have the ingredients to do&amp;nbsp;so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let say you&amp;#8217;d want to find something to work on, related to this repo.
Usually (but not always), there&amp;#8217;s an issue related what you&amp;#8217;d be working on.
You can either report an issue yourself before starting a change, or you can
pick up an issue and say you&amp;#8217;d like to work on it. The &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;issues&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; tab on the
original repository (the upstream, not yours) would be the place to start. For
instance, I&amp;#8217;ve added two issues on our example and it looks&amp;nbsp;like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/issues.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now assume you&amp;#8217;d like to work on the &amp;#8220;Explain what this repository is&amp;#8221; issue.
It states what should be done, and you can leave a comment saying you&amp;#8217;ll fix
it. It&amp;#8217;ll be different for you since you&amp;#8217;re not a member/maintainer of the
repo, but it&amp;#8217;ll look similar to this&amp;nbsp;one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/issue-1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please also note that on the right side of the title of the issue, and in the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; of the issue, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; of the issue is mentioned, which is 1 in this case
(the first issue in the repository); we&amp;#8217;ll get back to it&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to your local copy of the repo, you can start contributing using a
&lt;em&gt;git workflow&lt;/em&gt;, which involves proper &lt;em&gt;branching&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;merging&lt;/em&gt; and so on.
There are different ways you can do that, and with a quick search you&amp;#8217;ll find
proposals such as &lt;a href="https://sandofsky.com/blog/git-workflow.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; one. It&amp;#8217;s good
to go through some of those and familiarize yourself with the process, but it&amp;#8217;s
not a must. Those workflows become more important if a few collaborators start
working on the same repository, which would happen in an organization and
specially on a GitLab platform. However, since you&amp;#8217;ll be doing everything on
your own repository and not the upstream, you can do whatever you want without
disturbing the &lt;em&gt;upstream&lt;/em&gt;. Something they all have in common is the concept of
a &lt;strong&gt;branch&lt;/strong&gt;. As &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-Branches-in-a-Nutshell"&gt;the book has
it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCS&lt;/span&gt; [(Version Control System)] has some form of branching
support. Branching means you diverge from the main line of development and
continue to do work without messing with that main line. In many &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCS&lt;/span&gt; tools,
this is a somewhat expensive process, often requiring you to create a new
copy of your source code directory, which can take a long time for large&amp;nbsp;projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people refer to Git’s branching model as its “killer feature,” and it
certainly sets Git apart in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VCS&lt;/span&gt; community. Why is it so special? The way
Git branches is incredibly lightweight, making branching operations nearly
instantaneous, and switching back and forth between branches generally just
as fast. Unlike many other VCSs, Git encourages workflows that branch and
merge often, even multiple times in a day. Understanding and mastering this
feature gives you a powerful and unique tool and can entirely change the way
that you&amp;nbsp;develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main branch is always &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;. Another main branch in a project may be
&lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;devel&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt;, but not all projects have it, and it depends on
the kind of &lt;em&gt;workflow&lt;/em&gt; they choose to follow. If they choose to have &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;
very stable and corresponding to the latest release, then the main development
would happen on &lt;code&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt;. On the other hand, if they decide to have release
branches and have the main development happen on &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;, they&amp;#8217;ll probably not
have the &lt;code&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; branch and instead have branches such as &lt;code&gt;v1.2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;v1.3&lt;/code&gt;,
etc. You usually would need to &lt;em&gt;base&lt;/em&gt; your development on the active and under
development branch. When you &lt;em&gt;fork&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;clone&lt;/em&gt; a repository, it also includes
all the branches that repository, and you can simply change to that branch&amp;nbsp;locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see the branch you have as active&amp;nbsp;using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git status
On branch master
nothing to commit, working tree clean
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, by default you&amp;#8217;re on the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch. Now since &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; is
our main development branch, you can base your work on it and create a branch
from it. You can create a branch based on your current active branch&amp;nbsp;using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git branch &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
$ git status
On branch master
nothing to commit, working tree clean
$ git branch --list
* master
  &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we created a branch, but still stayed on master. In order to
change to the newly created branch, you should &lt;strong&gt;checkout&lt;/strong&gt; the&amp;nbsp;branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git checkout &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
Switched to branch &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;test&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
$ git branch --list
  master
* &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also go back to &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;, and safely delete this &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git checkout master
Switched to branch &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;master&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
$ git branch -D &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
Deleted branch &lt;span class="nb"&gt;test&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;was ea65abd&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.
$ git branch --list
* master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ea65abd&lt;/code&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;abbreviated commit hash&lt;/em&gt; which you can ignore for&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more convenient way to create a new branch and check it out at the same time
would&amp;nbsp;be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git checkout -b doc/readme
Switched to a new branch &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;doc/readme&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the name of the new branch is &lt;code&gt;doc/readme&lt;/code&gt;. The name can be
almost anything, and one convention that some people follow is to name branches
as &lt;code&gt;category/item&lt;/code&gt;, but you could as well do &lt;code&gt;category-item&lt;/code&gt;, or
&lt;code&gt;my-random-branch-name&lt;/code&gt;. I&amp;#8217;d suggest you always keep your master clean and in
sync with your remote, and only work on branches for each&amp;nbsp;feature/issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can finally start working on the issue. This is the &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ cat README.md 
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# example-repo&lt;/span&gt;
example repository &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; github tutorials
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And let&amp;#8217;s change it&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ cat README.md 
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# example-repo&lt;/span&gt;
example repository &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; github tutorials

This repository is made to showcase some common tasks and processes on GitHub
and to present the related &lt;span class="sb"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;git&lt;span class="sb"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt; commands. The post explaining these processes
is located
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;here&lt;span class="o"&gt;](&lt;/span&gt;gitgithub-how-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project-on-github.html&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;#8217;s see what the status of the local repo&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git status
On branch doc/readme
Changes not staged &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; commit:
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;use &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;git add &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;...&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; to update what will be committed&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;use &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;git checkout -- &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;...&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; to discard changes in working directory&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    modified:   README.md

no changes added to commit &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;use &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;git add&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; and/or &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;git commit -a&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it says the &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; file is &lt;strong&gt;modified&lt;/strong&gt;. You would need to
&lt;strong&gt;add&lt;/strong&gt; the file. That brings us to the lifecycle of a file on a git repo. As
shown in &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Recording-Changes-to-the-Repository"&gt;the
book&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/lifecycle.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the 4 states a file can have under the&amp;nbsp;repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Untracked&lt;/em&gt;: the file exists in the project tree, but it&amp;#8217;s not being tracked
  by&amp;nbsp;git.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unmodified&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; won&amp;#8217;t report any of these files, since there has
  been no changes to them since the last &lt;em&gt;snapshot&lt;/em&gt; git has taken from them.
  That snapshot happens when you &lt;strong&gt;commit&lt;/strong&gt; the changes to&amp;nbsp;files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modified&lt;/em&gt;: the previous version of the file is recorded in the git repo, but
  since then, there has been changes to it, and these changes are not recorded&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staged&lt;/em&gt;: there has been changes to the file since the last &lt;em&gt;snapshot&lt;/em&gt;, and
  these changes are set to be recorded by a &lt;strong&gt;commit&lt;/strong&gt;, but that commit hasn&amp;#8217;t
  happened&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more comprehensive explanation of how to record changes in the repo can be
found
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Recording-Changes-to-the-Repository"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we need to move the &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;em&gt;modified&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;staged&lt;/em&gt; (using &lt;code&gt;git
add&lt;/code&gt;), and then to &lt;em&gt;unmodified&lt;/em&gt; (using &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git add README.md
$ git commit -m &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;added required changes to the README.md&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Always include a message with the commit. Meaningful &lt;em&gt;Commit messages&lt;/em&gt; are
extremely helpful for later coming back and finding some changes you&amp;#8217;ve made
previously. Alternatively, you could summarize the above two commands in&amp;nbsp;one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git commit -am &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;added required changes to the README.md&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;doc/readme b43f0b6&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; added required changes to the README.md
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; file changed, &lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; insertions&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;+&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
$ git status
On branch doc/readme
nothing to commit, working tree clean
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference is that &lt;code&gt;git commit -a&lt;/code&gt; adds all modified files to the staging
area, which may not be what you want. For more control you can use the two
separate commands. Also, as you can see, the working tree is &lt;em&gt;clean&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;#8217;s time to &lt;strong&gt;push&lt;/strong&gt; the changes to our remote copy of the repository,
which we can do by &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ git push
fatal: The current branch doc/readme has no upstream branch.
To push the current branch and &lt;span class="nb"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; the remote as upstream, use

    git push --set-upstream origin doc/readme
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OOPS&lt;/span&gt;, it failed, because there is no corresponding branch on the remote copy
which corresponds to the local branch we&amp;#8217;ve made. Your own remote copy is the
&lt;em&gt;upstream&lt;/em&gt; to the local copy, and you see that you need to tell git which
branch on the upstream should be the corresponding one. As you can see, by
default it suggests the same branch name, on the &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; remote. The suggested
command would create a new branch on your remote copy, and upload the changes
to that&amp;nbsp;branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;git&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;push&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;upstream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;origin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Enumerating&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Counting&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Delta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;compression&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;up&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;threads&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Compressing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Writing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;461&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bytes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;461.00&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;KiB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Total&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;delta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reused&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;delta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Create&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pull&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;request&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;GitHub&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;visiting&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class="nl"&gt;https&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;//github.com/adrinjalali/example-repo/pull/new/doc/readme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="n"&gt;To&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;github&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;adrinjalali&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;example&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;repo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;git&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;branch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Branch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;up&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;track&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;branch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;readme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;origin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your output would be slightly different. Here I had to change my remote and use
the ssh connection instead. Not only it&amp;#8217;s more secure, it also allows you to
interact with your account without the need to enter your username/password
every time you need permissions. You can find the guides to setup that for your
account
&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/connecting-to-github-with-ssh/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I also
recommend activating a two factor authentication (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;2FA&lt;/span&gt;) for your&amp;nbsp;account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you go back to your account and check the repository, you&amp;#8217;ll see that a
new branch has been&amp;nbsp;created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="git/github" src="files/img/git/github-branches.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have the changes on your account, you can go ahead and create the
first &lt;strong&gt;pull request&lt;/strong&gt;. It basically means you&amp;#8217;d send a request to the
maintainers of the repository to pull the changes you&amp;#8217;ve made, from your repo
into the original repo. For that, you also need to specify your &lt;code&gt;doc/readme&lt;/code&gt;
branch as the &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; branch, and the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; on the original repo as the &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;
branch. Please note that it would be the &lt;em&gt;develop&lt;/em&gt; branch on the upstream repo
if that was what you based your changes on. But in this case, we based the
changes on the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch of the upstream&amp;nbsp;repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you could click on the &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Compare &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; pull request&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; button, or you could go
to the upstream repository, then &lt;em&gt;Pull requests&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;), and then &lt;em&gt;New pull
request&lt;/em&gt;, which brings you to a page where you can explain what the does and
then create&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you create the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;, you can wait for reviewers to review your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;, which
usually means they&amp;#8217;ll ask you to change a few things. To apply those changes,
you don&amp;#8217;t need to create a new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt; or a new branch, you simply need to be sure
you&amp;#8217;re on the same branch as before, apply your changes, commit to your local
clone (&lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt; commands), and then push (&lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;). This will
add your changes to your existing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this helps a few people a little bit. I&amp;#8217;d be happy to get some feedback
and see if it&amp;#8217;s helpful or&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:f1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chacon, Scott, and Ben Straub. Pro git. Apress, 2014.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:f1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Open Source - CoC - Conflicts</title><link href="https://adrin.info/open-source-coc-conflicts.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2020-04-12:/open-source-coc-conflicts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.stalawfirm.com/en/news/view/jordanian-code-of-conduct.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="CoC" src="files/img/code-of-conduct1-min.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Since I don&amp;#8217;t know individuals&amp;#8217; pronouns involved in this post, &lt;em&gt;they/them&lt;/em&gt; is
used&amp;nbsp;instead.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post was triggered by three of PyTest maintainers leaving the project in a
single day. That&amp;#8217;s 3 out of 4-5 active developers of a project which is relied
on by a massive …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.stalawfirm.com/en/news/view/jordanian-code-of-conduct.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="CoC" src="files/img/code-of-conduct1-min.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Since I don&amp;#8217;t know individuals&amp;#8217; pronouns involved in this post, &lt;em&gt;they/them&lt;/em&gt; is
used&amp;nbsp;instead.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post was triggered by three of PyTest maintainers leaving the project in a
single day. That&amp;#8217;s 3 out of 4-5 active developers of a project which is relied
on by a massive part of the ecosystem to test their projects/software/library.
So it really is a big deal (obviously not as big of a deal as covid19 which is
happening these days ;)&amp;nbsp;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first person to leave was &lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/pytest-dev/2020-April/004939.html"&gt;Bruno
Oliveira&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi&amp;nbsp;everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past years I&amp;#8217;ve been part of pytest, which is an awesome library
and also a community with awesome people. It definitely made me a better
person and better&amp;nbsp;programmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the past months or so one individual has drained my will to work
on the project because of his interactions, so I decided it is best that I
leave the project for a while and focus on other&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I of course wish the project and everyone involved the best, and will
definitely continue to work on my numerous plugins&amp;nbsp;meanwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay safe, and&amp;nbsp;cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruno&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately after &lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/pytest-dev/2020-April/004940.html"&gt;Anthony
Sottile&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/pytest-dev/2020-April/004941.html"&gt;Ronny
Pfannschmidt&lt;/a&gt;
left for a similar reason. It seems there have been discussions in PyTest&amp;#8217;s CoC
committee which have not come to a satisfying conclusion: judging from the fact
that two of the three developers who have stepped down are/were in PyTest&amp;#8217;s CoC
(Code of Conduct) team, one of them &lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pull/6857"&gt;removing themself from the
committee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://mail.python.org/pipermail/pytest-dev/2020-April/004945.html"&gt;this
email&lt;/a&gt; by
Brianna, another member of the CoC&amp;nbsp;team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi&amp;nbsp;all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of the Code of Conduct (CoC) committee members (
https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/blob/master/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md ) I
want to apologise for the poor handling of issues that have led Bruno,
Anthony and Ronny to step back from the project. As a group we failed to
act decisively and now people who have contributed so much to pytest are
suffering, and for that I am&amp;nbsp;sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to reach out to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSF&lt;/span&gt; Conduct Working Group and ask them to
advise us on a way&amp;nbsp;forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thanks,&amp;nbsp;Brianna&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m very curious to see how it unfolds and what the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSF&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s CoC team thinks about
the issue, but having my CoC related experience (writing them, serving in CoC
committees, dealing with the same issues in other open source projects, etc.),
I don&amp;#8217;t think there&amp;#8217;s an easy answer to the&amp;nbsp;issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before talking about potential solutions, we need to understand what has been
happening. It is really important to note that &lt;strong&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not a PyTest
developer/maintainer and I&amp;#8217;m trying to understand the issue from an outsider&amp;#8217;s
perspective, and the reason I&amp;#8217;m writing this post is that this issue is by far
not unique to PyTest, and as a community we need to be better equipped to deal
with such issues&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems the individual in question is &lt;a href="https://github.com/blueyed"&gt;Daniel
Hahler&lt;/a&gt; who has been very active in PyTest&amp;#8217;s
development since about &lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/graphs/contributors?from=2017-04-22&amp;amp;to=2020-04-11&amp;amp;type=c"&gt;June
2019&lt;/a&gt;.
Unfortunately, not all interactions with this person have been productive or
pleasant. As an example of an interaction which has frustrated Bruno, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nicoddemus/status/1248946262453424130?s=20"&gt;they
have pointed&lt;/a&gt;
to &lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pull/6663#discussion_r375763028"&gt;this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;/comment
thread&lt;/a&gt;,
which I completely agree is a very unpleasant interaction. However, when it
comes to CoC violations, if I were in PyTest&amp;#8217;s CoC committee, I would have a
hard time deciding whether this single instance warrants banning Danial from
the project or not. Therefore I decided to dig in and see how other
interactions with them look.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aopen+involves%3Ablueyed"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;
you can see the list of PRs where Daniel has been involved either as the author
or as a reviewer. A quick look at the conversations shows that clearly not all
interactions are hostile, but by looking at just the first page, I found these
examples clearly not nice:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pull/7029"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pull/6934"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/pull/6840"&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;. One could argue that some
of the frustrations are miscommunications or cultural differences; but even
then, my judgment is that they are not constructive or respectful, at&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now putting all the instances together, it is very clear to me that this person
is creating an unpleasant and disrespectful environment. But does this warrant
Daniel&amp;#8217;s removal from the team? &lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest/blob/master/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md"&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s PyTest&amp;#8217;s
CoC&lt;/a&gt;, and
as examples of expected behavior it&amp;nbsp;states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being respectful of differing viewpoints and&amp;nbsp;experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gracefully accepting constructive&amp;nbsp;criticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the enforcement section, it&amp;nbsp;states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project maintainers who do not follow or enforce the Code of Conduct in good
faith may face temporary or permanent repercussions as determined by other
members of the project&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this seems like a very clear case of violation to me, and the CoC seems to
have defined a clear consequence of those violations. Then why is this person
still on the&amp;nbsp;project?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately dealing with CoC cases is usually very complicated and in my
experience, even in cases where it seems very clear what the judgment should
be, the committee does not easily agree on a single course of action, as very
apparent from this case as well. Let&amp;#8217;s talk about some of the&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intent vs Impact: Some would argue that the person violating the CoC did not
  &lt;em&gt;intend&lt;/em&gt; to disrespect or harass anybody, and that&amp;#8217;s more important than the
  impact the interaction has had on the disrespected/harassed person. These
  days I personally don&amp;#8217;t really agree with the argument, especially after
  reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4455729-35-dumb-things-well-intended-people-say"&gt;35 Dumb Things Well-Intended People Say: Surprising Things We Say
  That Widen The Diversity
  Gap&lt;/a&gt;.
  As individuals, we should be aware of the consequences and the impact of our
  actions and watch for&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Considering the accused&amp;#8217;s position in the community: I think the most
  infamous example is &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2013/02/linus-torvalds-i-will-not-change-linux-to-deep-throat-microsoft/"&gt;Linus Trovalds&amp;#8217; many aggressive
  emails&lt;/a&gt;
  in the Linux Kernel community, and the community not reacting with an
  appropriate response. When people are in a position of power or influence, it
  makes it harder for the community or a CoC committee to act decisively. They
  don&amp;#8217;t have to be the sole owner of the
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benevolent_dictator_for_life"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BDFL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the
  project to make it hard to deal with; being a main contributor makes it hard&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The accused being a peer: In many cases including this PyTest incidence, the
  accused is in a way a peer to the members of the CoC committee, who are also
  maintainers of the same project. This makes it really hard to deal with the
  case, since most people would rather try and &lt;em&gt;resolve&lt;/em&gt; the issue in one way
  or another, which does not involve banning their peer from the community.
  Most people would rather resolve the issue in the &lt;em&gt;nicest&lt;/em&gt; way&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, these [and many other] reasons prevent a candid, timely, and
decisive decision by the CoC committee. However, understanding the challenges
does not make individuals who feel strongly about the issue feel better about
the indecisiveness or lack of action, and as somebody who has been in that
position, I completely understand&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can we do to improve the&amp;nbsp;situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe having external people in the CoC team helps with providing an
outsider&amp;#8217;s perspective. They may have a more objective understanding of the
situation than people who are closely involved with the case. That said, many
teams may be averse to the idea since it would mean letting an &lt;em&gt;outsider&lt;/em&gt;
in the team, and in a place which is very intimate and close to the heart of
many communities. Understandably, people don&amp;#8217;t want to &lt;em&gt;give control&lt;/em&gt; to an
outsider. However, our community is larger than a single project&amp;#8217;s community,
and we could help each other out. This doesn&amp;#8217;t have to be a centralized place
like the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PSF&lt;/span&gt; to handle all the cases (of course they can be a great place for
advice), instead it could be a group of trusted and respected people who are
rather experienced and concerned about these issues, and could sit in different
CoC&amp;nbsp;committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that handling CoC cases is hard, unpleasant, and is not a
trivial skill. Unfortunately in the broader community we don&amp;#8217;t really
appreciate these skills [yet] and most people are extremely inexperienced in
this regard. As a consequence, when a project appoints a CoC committee, most
probably many members of the committee have not had any experience handling CoC&amp;nbsp;cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember after handling a difficult CoC case, I reached out to people who
were CoC contacts of different projects to inquire about enforceability of a
given CoC, and almost nobody had any satisfying answer. This is a result of us
as a community having no clue about how to enforce our CoCs, and sometimes the
legal challenges attached to the issue make it harder. For instance,
somebody violating a CoC may not be breaking any laws (CoC are usually more
strict than the laws of the given country), and therefore it is really tricky
to enforce that CoC in a &lt;em&gt;public&lt;/em&gt; event. This and many other related details
are not things which you can expect a usual developer in a project to know&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I see it, our communities have embraced having a code of conduct in one way
or another. These CoCs may not be perfect, but they&amp;#8217;re a step towards the right
direction (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IMO&lt;/span&gt;). Then we had issues enforcing and actually implementing them,
and larger communities who have already had cases are now more equipped with
the tools they need to handle the cases. What needs to happen next, is for us
to openly talk about our cases without revealing the identities of people
involved. We should have a conversation about the details, and learn from one
another. We should also celebrate people who know how to handle these cases,
know them, and reach out for help when we&amp;#8217;re not sure what to&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m very happy that this incident has attracted some attention in the
community, and I hope we learn from it and keep our communities more respectful
and healthier than what they are now. Afterall, this is one of the reasons we
are not really good at diversity and inclusion in our communities and improving
on this front would help with D&amp;amp;I as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="community"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>scikit-learn sprint at Nairobi, Kenya</title><link href="https://adrin.info/scikit-learn-sprint-at-nairobi-kenya.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2019-06-25:/scikit-learn-sprint-at-nairobi-kenya.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nairobi/sklearn" src="files/img/nairobi-sklearn.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, after being the co-speaker of a &amp;#8220;My first open source
contribution&amp;#8221; talk at PyData Berlin 2018, I myself became very motivated and
started actively contributing to the &lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt; project. I was surprised to
see how much I could and had to learn to improve my contributions …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nairobi/sklearn" src="files/img/nairobi-sklearn.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, after being the co-speaker of a &amp;#8220;My first open source
contribution&amp;#8221; talk at PyData Berlin 2018, I myself became very motivated and
started actively contributing to the &lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt; project. I was surprised to
see how much I could and had to learn to improve my contributions, and that was
after over 20 years of programming experience, 6 years of which I did mostly
Python, and several years of working in the industry. It wasn&amp;#8217;t even the first
time I was contributing to an open source project, but it was the first time I
was actively looking for issues to&amp;nbsp;fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I stayed on the project, was the extremely nice and patient
attitude of the reviewers and core developers of the project, most importantly,
Joel Nothman. I felt welcomed, tutored, and guided throughout my contributions.
Of course it also required my patience, since some of the contributions would
go through a long iteration process, even though they were only a few lines of
example code. After a while I was more confident taking over some of the more
challenging tasks, and it felt more rewarding as they became more&amp;nbsp;challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day in December (2018), I woke up to find an email in my inbox which said
they&amp;#8217;d like to have me as a core developer, and if I&amp;#8217;d accept. There are very
few instances in my life in which I remember such a feeling of happiness
flowing through my whole existence. I accepted with joy, and there I was with
a whole bunch of new responsibilities added to my shoulders; but the kind which
make me want to wake up in the morning to take care&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also happened to be the case that the core team was planning a sprint in
Paris to go be together and work on issues in person for a few days. I joined
that sprint, in February, where we worked for a whole week, 9am to 10pm more or
less. It was so stimulating that I did not realize how exhausted I had become.
When I went back home, it took me quite a few days to recover, but it was one
of the best weeks of my life, working with brilliant people from all around the
world. It was also really good for the project, since we managed to solve some
of the very long standing issues of the project, which had been open for&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a while after that when I saw an email in the mailing list, asking if
somebody could give a hand for a sprint being planned in Nairobi, Kenya. It was
going to be organized by Women in Machine Learning and Data Science
(&lt;a href="http://wimlds.org/"&gt;WiMLDS&lt;/a&gt;), and since it was the combination of two things
very close to my heart (diversity and open source), I made sure to respond to
it and offer my help &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASAP&lt;/span&gt;. Reshama Shaikh, the main organizer from the WiMLDS
side, got back to me shortly and we started planning for the sprint. What I did
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOT&lt;/span&gt; know, was that they were planning to fly a contributor to Nairobi to be
there in person for the sprint, which I found a very nice&amp;nbsp;surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it took around 4 months of planning which I was involved with,
including vaccination, visa, etc. I don&amp;#8217;t think we even planned the sprint in
Paris this much, but Reshama and Mariam Haji (the main organizer in Nairobi)
were both very thorough and planned everything to the last bit of it. So I flew
to Nairobi, stayed there for 2 days, and had the sprint on a Saturday. We ended
up having about 40 attendees, almost all new to open source, and by the end of
the day we had over 20 open pull requests (PRs) generated by them on that
single&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s so gratifying to see the joy in people&amp;#8217;s face when they open their first
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt; and receive feedback from the core developers. I always love to see their
faces when they start touching the files of the package, which they&amp;#8217;ve used
till then as a user. I still remember the feeling of sending a patch for an
open source project for the first time (before &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; was invented), and when I
see those same feelings in new contributors faces, it pushes all the exhaustion
out of my&amp;nbsp;being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d say it was a very successful sprint, specially since quite a few of the
contributors we had there, are still contributing and opening new PRs even
afterwards. To me, that&amp;#8217;s what a sprint for new contributors is for, to enable
them and break all the barriers they feel having in front of them, and have
them motivated enough that they continue contributing&amp;nbsp;afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I think there are still a few things which could be improved and I&amp;#8217;m
noting them here mostly for my own future&amp;nbsp;reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a trade off between how much information the instructor tries to give
to the audience, before they jump into finding issues to work on, and how much
time is left for them to contribute. I kept the introduction very short, and
just pointed them to the part of the documentation where they could follow the
instructions and start working on issues. I did that mostly because I
personally don&amp;#8217;t find those slide based talks very productive. However, I
figured most people were lost, and they were not even sure which question to
ask or where to start. What helped, was that I found a minor issue in the
documentation, and fixed it and submitted a corresponding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;, while sharing my
screen. Immediately after that it felt like the room now knows much better what
they&amp;#8217;re doing. I would have one of those ready next time, and have kind of a
hands on tutorial on contributing, &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, and GitHub&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing which I think we should improve in &lt;code&gt;sklearn&lt;/code&gt; documentation, is
the guide for people to setup their environments. There were people who were
still trying to setup their environment and get the package to compile still at
the end of the day, and that to me is a strong hint that something could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point is that it was a weekend, and most core developers were either
sleeping or not at their PCs. Being the sole person trying to review the PRs as
they come and at the same time to answer the questions on-site, is almost not
manageable. I&amp;#8217;d try to coordinate with at least one other core developer to be
online during the sprint, before the sprint this&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I loved everything related to this sprint, and I hope we get to do it
again next year&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Ways to contribute to open source projects!</title><link href="https://adrin.info/ways-to-contribute-to-open-source-projects.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-27:/ways-to-contribute-to-open-source-projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/20181027-opensource.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code is not the only way you can contribute to an open source project.
Like any other project, there are many tasks which are not programming, but are
required to push the project forward, and many programmers are not even
necessarily good at those tasks. Think of organizing meetups …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/20181027-opensource.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code is not the only way you can contribute to an open source project.
Like any other project, there are many tasks which are not programming, but are
required to push the project forward, and many programmers are not even
necessarily good at those tasks. Think of organizing meetups, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UX&lt;/span&gt; design,
documentation, and translation as some examples. You can read more about these
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/life/16/1/8-ways-contribute-open-source-without-writing-code"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is by far not an exhaustive list of what can be done, rather what I
have personally been engaged with. Let&amp;#8217;s assume you start using a piece of
software as a library in of your projects, and through time you want to get
engaged with it&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please always remember that many of these packages are maintained by volunteers
and they&amp;#8217;re not always immediately available to respond to your questions,
suggestions, or contributions, so be&amp;nbsp;patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a user, one of the first things you may do is to read the documentation of
the package (and hopefully that exists for the package you&amp;#8217;re going to use). For
most libraries out there, the documentation may be sparse, incomplete, or at
times incomprehensible. Although in some cases it may be the case that you need
to cover some background to better understand what you&amp;#8217;re reading, but in most
cases it&amp;#8217;s the documentation you&amp;#8217;re reading which is not perfect. Unfortunately,
it&amp;#8217;s not easy to convince core developers to write good and extensive
documentation, since they&amp;#8217;re mostly busy implementing new features or fixing
reported bugs and&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some packages allow you to suggest an edit to the documentation on the fly, from
the browser itself, which removes the initial barrier for many to start
contributing.
&lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/current/getting-started.html"&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt;
is a good example. As a new user, you probably pay attention to the
documentation probably more than anybody else. Therefore you may find mistakes
or see potential easy improvements which are usually not noticed by other more
experienced users and developers. Be encouraged to suggest any change you deem
appropriate. It may be accepted immediately, or it may start a whole
conversation about a certain aspect of the software. Some of my contributions
have been as small as a punctuation, to make the sentence a bit easier to&amp;nbsp;understand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>How to find a good open source project for contributions?</title><link href="https://adrin.info/how-to-find-a-good-open-source-project-for-contributions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-13:/how-to-find-a-good-open-source-project-for-contributions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Diversity" src="files/img/foss-diversity.jpg" title="Credit: https://blog.mapbox.com/our-code-of-conduct-for-open-source-2b3a81c00c80"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a project to which you&amp;#8217;d like to contribute, there are two
major aspects you may want to consider. One is the way it&amp;#8217;s released and
managed, and the other is the community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see the first aspect, it&amp;#8217;s like a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Diversity" src="files/img/foss-diversity.jpg" title="Credit: https://blog.mapbox.com/our-code-of-conduct-for-open-source-2b3a81c00c80"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a project to which you&amp;#8217;d like to contribute, there are two
major aspects you may want to consider. One is the way it&amp;#8217;s released and
managed, and the other is the community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see the first aspect, it&amp;#8217;s like a spectrum. Closed source proprietary
software on one side (let say the right side), and community driven and fully 
transparent and open
sourced project on the other side (let say the left side).
And it&amp;#8217;s important to realize that different
projects are somewhere on this spectrum, and not necessarily on either of the
two ends; let aside the whole licensing issue which itself complicates matters
by another order of&amp;nbsp;magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes companies &amp;#8220;release&amp;#8221; the source code of a product, or a part of a
product. Microsoft does this pretty often. You can only look at the code; you
can&amp;#8217;t run it, you can&amp;#8217;t use it, and most people won&amp;#8217;t. To me it&amp;#8217;s more like a
public relations thingy. They use it as a tool to gain reputation among the
community. I see such examples as the ones pretty close the right side of the&amp;nbsp;spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going slightly to the left side of the spectrum, there are projects which are
&amp;#8220;released&amp;#8221; as a whole, and they may even include a friendly license letting
you use it under certain conditions. They may even have a GitHub account and
dump the source code there. Some of these projects are released once, and never
maintained further, and some go through periodical releases; but they still
keep the public community mostly in dark about the development of the
new features. They usually also don&amp;#8217;t really welcome contributions from
&amp;#8220;outsiders&amp;#8221;, and that&amp;#8217;s not because they don&amp;#8217;t like contributions; it&amp;#8217;s mostly
due to the fact that they have limited amount of resources and their priorities
are dictated by the products in which these pieces of software are used. I&amp;#8217;m not
a big fan of contributing to these projects since a large part of the
conversation about the project happens within the team inside the company,
and external contributors are treated somewhat like a second order citizens to
these projects. I get the feeling that projects such as
&lt;a href="https://github.com/explosion/spaCy"&gt;spaCy&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tensorflow"&gt;tensorflow&lt;/a&gt; are such projects. They
have an extremely slow response rate on community questions. You do get the
feeling that it&amp;#8217;s a one sided relationship, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; they release a version,
and if you&amp;#8217;re lucky, your concerns may have been addressed in the&amp;nbsp;release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next group of projects are the ones which are considered as a part of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_and_open-source_software"&gt;free and open source software (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FOSS&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;.
This means not only the software is free and open source, but also volunteers
are encouraged to contribute to it and help it be improved. Naturally, if you&amp;#8217;d
like to work on a project as a volunteer, these are good candidates. But even
within this category of projects, not all of them are a friendly place to
contributors. Fortunately, more and more projects are moving towards having
a proper code of conduct ensuring a harassment free environment, and probably
the most high
profile one among the recent ones is the Linux Kernel project, which recently
confronted Linus Trovalds about it and adopted a
&lt;a href="https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux.git/commit/?id=8a104f8b5867c682d994ffa7a74093c54469c11f"&gt;new code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;.
It is important to realize that there&amp;#8217;s no such thing as the open source
community. The reality is that there are different communities around different
projects/topics. People&amp;#8217;s attitudes differ from community to community,
programming language to programming language,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal experience, which admittedly doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily project the
complete picture about any community since it&amp;#8217;s by definition subjective, has
been the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt; community has always been the harshest in my experience (and I know
  I&amp;#8217;m not alone having experienced that). If you ask a question there which
  sounds &lt;em&gt;stupid&lt;/em&gt; to the experts in the field, they probably would crush you by
  asking why you haven&amp;#8217;t read a &amp;#8220;proper&amp;#8221; book on C++. By that they usually
  mean the whole C++ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; community was really unpleasant to interact, to the point it encouraged
  me to switch from R to Python (yeah, that is in fact why I became a python
  coder). After creating and maintaining three packages for R in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; and
  Bioconductor, I was kinda done with it. I need to mention that this was back
  in 2012, and a lot could have changed in these few years. I have no idea how
  the community behaves these days; and I&amp;#8217;d be delighted if I&amp;#8217;m completely wrong
  about the community&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; has always been nice as far as I&amp;#8217;m concerned. It is a language
  which has it&amp;#8217;s
  &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/codeofconduct/"&gt;own code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;. You can
  imagine how that has influenced the whole community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things you can consider when checking on a [&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FOSS&lt;/span&gt;]&amp;nbsp;project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Activity&lt;/strong&gt;: Is the project under active development? When was the last
  release? How often people open issues and contribute to the project? How often
  do main developers respond to those issues? Many projects may seem pretty cool
  at the first glance, but when you dig deeper, they may be dead projects. Sure
  you can try to revive it, but that may require more dedication and time than
  what you have at&amp;nbsp;hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/strong&gt;: The presence of a code of conduct is neither a necessary
  nor a sufficient condition for a healthy atmosphere in a project, but it&amp;#8217;s a
  sign that the core developers do care about the kind of atmosphere around the
  project. Also, the more people care about codes of conducts, the more pressure
  on the projects to adopt&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Contributions&lt;/strong&gt;: For larger projects, you can check how open the
  community is, by checking the repository logs. There are many tools to
  visualize activity on repositories, for instance, you can check the activity
  around tensorflow
  &lt;a href="http://ghv.artzub.com/#repo=tensorflow&amp;amp;climit=100&amp;amp;user=tensorflow"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
  and activity around scikit-learn
  &lt;a href="http://ghv.artzub.com/#repo=scikit-learn&amp;amp;climit=100&amp;amp;user=scikit-learn"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  You can easily notice how tensorflow has a special user called
  &lt;em&gt;tensorflow-gardener&lt;/em&gt;, and you can read about it
  &lt;a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/how-the-tensorflow-team-handles-open-source-support"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  I personally prefer repositories which have a larger set of contributors
  publicly contributing to the ones hiding internal development behind a special&amp;nbsp;user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treating Contributors&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;#8217;s never pleasant to work with a bunch of snobs!
  As a new contributor, you are bound to make many mistakes, or try things the
  way which is not the common way it&amp;#8217;s done in the project you&amp;#8217;re working on.
  This is
  normal and expected as users join a community. It is very important for the
  core developers of that project to know that and treat newcommers nicely
  and encouragingly. You can see if that&amp;#8217;s the case or not, by going through
  some of the issues and pull requests in the project you&amp;#8217;re checking. Just
  take your time and read some of the conversations happening around some of
  the issues to make sure it suits your taste. You can also check the &amp;#8220;closed&amp;#8221;
  issues
  to see how the core developers handle closing&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another post I&amp;#8217;ll talk about ways you can start contributing to a project
of your&amp;nbsp;choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Why would you want to contribute to an open source project?</title><link href="https://adrin.info/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-09:/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be taken into account here, and here I try
to go through some of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the community&lt;/strong&gt; by contributing to the project. This is the one which
   comes to one&amp;#8217;s mind the most. You like a product, or a community around a
   particular software, hence you contribute to that particular software. Doing
   so, you help yourself (if you use the software) and everybody else who uses
   that same&amp;nbsp;product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the larger community&lt;/strong&gt; by advocating and normalizing open source
   contributions. When you contribute to open source projects, you become yet
   another person who does that and it demystifies open source contributions
   for people around you. Many people (if not most) think you need to be a
   proficient programmer for an open source contributions, not realizing many
   contributions are not even in the form of code. If you work in a place where
   you use those projects in your products, it would make you and your
   colleagues realize how much work goes into those projects, and how your 
   company could benefit from spending time improving it as a part of your&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal recognition&lt;/strong&gt; due to those contributions. Although your first
   contributions may be small, they&amp;#8217;ll grow and become more substantial if you
   stay persistent in your contributions. Sooner or later you become a core
   member of the community you work with, and you&amp;#8217;ll be recognized as such.
   Unlike your contributions to the closed source products in whatever company
   you work, the open source contributions are out there and you don&amp;#8217;t ever
   need to prove that you&amp;#8217;ve done them. It becomes a provable part of your
   professional&amp;nbsp;portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free mentors&lt;/strong&gt; while your contribution gets reviewed. This is only true
   for the friendly and nice project communities, and fortunately their number
   is growing. For quite a few years, if not decades, open source communities
   were mostly toxic, but that&amp;#8217;s changing and people are becoming nicer and
   more patient with newcomers. This means you shouldn&amp;#8217;t fear contributing,
   since the core developers of the project would help you go through the
   process and get your contribution up to the standards of the project. This
   also helps you gain experience working in a larger and more diverse team,
   and feel all the perks and challenges that come with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately not many places encourage their employees and colleagues to
have open source contributions, but still, I don&amp;#8217;t know of a place which would
dislike a candidate who has had some contributions which they can see and check.
Maybe half the job offers I get are because of my presence in the open source&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don&amp;#8217;t accept a job offer which involves no open source
contributions, and I always check what contributions the company and their
employees have. At least in Berlin, the scene is changing fast, and it&amp;#8217;s
becoming somewhat embarrassing for companies not to have any open source
product, and many of them are working on improving on this front. This is partly
due to the fact that many developers prefer an open and transparent company,
and open source is just a part of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the end, the more people contribute to these projects, the more pressure
it puts on companies to include themselves in this movement, which benefits
the larger open source software&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll talk about what these contributions mean, and how one could start
contributing in a separate&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry></feed>