<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Adrin Jalali - open-source</title><link href="http://adrin.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://adrin.info/feeds/open-source.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://adrin.info/</id><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Why would you want to contribute to an open source project?</title><link href="http://adrin.info/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2017-12-06:/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be taken into account here, and here I try
to go through some of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the community&lt;/strong&gt; by contributing to the project. This is the one which
   comes to one&amp;#8217;s mind the most. You like a product, or a community around a
   particular software, hence you contribute to that particular software. Doing
   so, you help yourself (if you use the software) and everybody else who uses
   that same&amp;nbsp;product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the larger community&lt;/strong&gt; by advocating and normalizing open source
   contributions. When you contribute to open source projects, you become yet
   another person who does that and it demystifies open source contributions
   for people around you. Many people (if not most) think you need to be a
   proficient programmer for an open source contributions, not realizing many
   contributions are not even in the form of code. If you work in a place where
   you use those projects in your products, it would make you and your
   colleagues realize how much work goes into those projects, and how your 
   company could benefit from spending time improving it as a part of your&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal recognition&lt;/strong&gt; due to those contributions. Although your first
   contributions may be small, they&amp;#8217;ll grow and become more substantial if you
   stay persistent in your contributions. Sooner or later you become a core
   member of the community you work with, and you&amp;#8217;ll be recognized as such.
   Unlike your contributions to the closed source products in whatever company
   you work, the open source contributions are out there and you don&amp;#8217;t ever
   need to prove that you&amp;#8217;ve done them. It becomes a provable part of your
   professional&amp;nbsp;portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free mentors&lt;/strong&gt; while your contribution gets reviewed. This is only true
   for the friendly and nice project communities, and fortunately their number
   is growing. For quite a few years, if not decades, open source communities
   where mostly toxic, but that&amp;#8217;s changing and people are becoming nicer and
   more patient with newcomers. This means you shouldn&amp;#8217;t fear contributing,
   since the core developers of the project would help you go through the
   process and get your contribution up to the standards of the project. This
   also helps you gain experience working in a larger and more diverse team,
   and feel all the perks and challenges that come with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately not many places encourage their employees and colleagues to
have open source contributions, but still, I don&amp;#8217;t know of a place which would
dislike a candidate who has had some contributions which they can see and check.
Maybe half the job offers I get are because of my presence in the open source&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don&amp;#8217;t accept a job offer which involves no open source
contributions, and I always check what contributions the company and their
employees have. At least in Berlin, the scene is changing fast, and it&amp;#8217;s
becoming somewhat embarrassing for companies not to have any open source
product, and many of them are working on improving on this front. This is partly
due to the fact that many developers prefer an open and transparent company,
and open source is just a part of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the end, the more people contribute to these projects, the more pressure
it puts on companies to include themselves in this movement, which benefits
the larger open source software&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll talk about what these contributions mean, and how one could start
contributing in a separate&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category></entry></feed>