<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Adrin Jalali - open-source</title><link href="https://adrin.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://adrin.info/feeds/open-source.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://adrin.info/</id><updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>scikit-learn sprint at Nairobi, Kenya</title><link href="https://adrin.info/scikit-learn-sprint-at-nairobi-kenya.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2019-06-25:/scikit-learn-sprint-at-nairobi-kenya.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nairobi/sklearn" src="files/img/nairobi-sklearn.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, after being the co-speaker of a &amp;#8220;My first open source
contribution&amp;#8221; talk at PyData Berlin 2018, I myself became very motivated and
started actively contributing to the &lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt; project. I was surprised to
see how much I could and had to learn to improve my contributions …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nairobi/sklearn" src="files/img/nairobi-sklearn.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, after being the co-speaker of a &amp;#8220;My first open source
contribution&amp;#8221; talk at PyData Berlin 2018, I myself became very motivated and
started actively contributing to the &lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt; project. I was surprised to
see how much I could and had to learn to improve my contributions, and that was
after over 20 years of programming experience, 6 years of which I did mostly
Python, and several years of working in the industry. It wasn&amp;#8217;t even the first
time I was contributing to an open source project, but it was the first time I
was actively looking for issues to&amp;nbsp;fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I stayed on the project, was the extremely nice and patient
attitude of the reviewers and core developers of the project, most importantly,
Joel Nothman. I felt welcomed, tutored, and guided throughout my contributions.
Of course it also required my patience, since some of the contributions would
go through a long iteration process, even though they were only a few lines of
example code. After a while I was more confident taking over some of the more
challenging tasks, and it felt more rewarding as they became more&amp;nbsp;challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day in December (2018), I woke up to find an email in my inbox which said
they&amp;#8217;d like to have me as a core developer, and if I&amp;#8217;d accept. There are very
few instances in my life in which I remember such a feeling of happiness
flowing through my whole existence. I accepted with joy, and there I was with
a whole bunch of new responsibilities added to my shoulders; but the kind which
make me want to wake up in the morning to take care&amp;nbsp;of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also happened to be the case that the core team was planning a sprint in
Paris to go be together and work on issues in person for a few days. I joined
that sprint, in February, where we worked for a whole week, 9am to 10pm more or
less. It was so stimulating that I did not realize how exhausted I had become.
When I went back home, it took me quite a few days to recover, but it was one
of the best weeks of my life, working with brilliant people from all around the
world. It was also really good for the project, since we managed to solve some
of the very long standing issues of the project, which had been open for&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a while after that when I saw an email in the mailing list, asking if
somebody could give a hand for a sprint being planned in Nairobi, Kenya. It was
going to be organized by Women in Machine Learning and Data Science
(&lt;a href="http://wimlds.org/"&gt;WiMLDS&lt;/a&gt;), and since it was the combination of two things
very close to my heart (diversity and open source), I made sure to respond to
it and offer my help &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASAP&lt;/span&gt;. Reshama Shaikh, the main organizer from the WiMLDS
side, got back to me shortly and we started planning for the sprint. What I did
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOT&lt;/span&gt; know, was that they were planning to fly a contributor to Nairobi to be
there in person for the sprint, which I found a very nice&amp;nbsp;surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it took around 4 months of planning which I was involved with,
including vaccination, visa, etc. I don&amp;#8217;t think we even planned the sprint in
Paris this much, but Reshama and Mariam Haji (the main organizer in Nairobi)
were both very thorough and planned everything to the last bit of it. So I flew
to Nairobi, stayed there for 2 days, and had the sprint on a Saturday. We ended
up having about 40 attendees, almost all new to open source, and by the end of
the day we had over 20 open pull requests (PRs) generated by them on that
single&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s so gratifying to see the joy in people&amp;#8217;s face when they open their first
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt; and receive feedback from the core developers. I always love to see their
faces when they start touching the files of the package, which they&amp;#8217;ve used
till then as a user. I still remember the feeling of sending a patch for an
open source project for the first time (before &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; was invented), and when I
see those same feelings in new contributors faces, it pushes all the exhaustion
out of my&amp;nbsp;being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d say it was a very successful sprint, specially since quite a few of the
contributors we had there, are still contributing and opening new PRs even
afterwards. To me, that&amp;#8217;s what a sprint for new contributors is for, to enable
them and break all the barriers they feel having in front of them, and have
them motivated enough that they continue contributing&amp;nbsp;afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I think there are still a few things which could be improved and I&amp;#8217;m
noting them here mostly for my own future&amp;nbsp;reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a trade off between how much information the instructor tries to give
to the audience, before they jump into finding issues to work on, and how much
time is left for them to contribute. I kept the introduction very short, and
just pointed them to the part of the documentation where they could follow the
instructions and start working on issues. I did that mostly because I
personally don&amp;#8217;t find those slide based talks very productive. However, I
figured most people were lost, and they were not even sure which question to
ask or where to start. What helped, was that I found a minor issue in the
documentation, and fixed it and submitted a corresponding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt;, while sharing my
screen. Immediately after that it felt like the room now knows much better what
they&amp;#8217;re doing. I would have one of those ready next time, and have kind of a
hands on tutorial on contributing, &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, and GitHub&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing which I think we should improve in &lt;code&gt;sklearn&lt;/code&gt; documentation, is
the guide for people to setup their environments. There were people who were
still trying to setup their environment and get the package to compile still at
the end of the day, and that to me is a strong hint that something could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point is that it was a weekend, and most core developers were either
sleeping or not at their PCs. Being the sole person trying to review the PRs as
they come and at the same time to answer the questions on-site, is almost not
manageable. I&amp;#8217;d try to coordinate with at least one other core developer to be
online during the sprint, before the sprint this&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I loved everything related to this sprint, and I hope we get to do it
again next year&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Ways to contribute to open source projects!</title><link href="https://adrin.info/ways-to-contribute-to-open-source-projects.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-27:/ways-to-contribute-to-open-source-projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/20181027-opensource.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code is not the only way you can contribute to an open source project.
Like any other project, there are many tasks which are not programming, but are
required to push the project forward, and many programmers are not even
necessarily good at those tasks. Think of organizing meetups …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/20181027-opensource.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code is not the only way you can contribute to an open source project.
Like any other project, there are many tasks which are not programming, but are
required to push the project forward, and many programmers are not even
necessarily good at those tasks. Think of organizing meetups, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UX&lt;/span&gt; design,
documentation, and translation as some examples. You can read more about these
&lt;a href="https://opensource.com/life/16/1/8-ways-contribute-open-source-without-writing-code"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is by far not an exhaustive list of what can be done, rather what I
have personally been engaged with. Let&amp;#8217;s assume you start using a piece of
software as a library in of your projects, and through time you want to get
engaged with it&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please always remember that many of these packages are maintained by volunteers
and they&amp;#8217;re not always immediately available to respond to your questions,
suggestions, or contributions, so be&amp;nbsp;patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a user, one of the first things you may do is to read the documentation of
the package (and hopefully that exists for the package you&amp;#8217;re going to use). For
most libraries out there, the documentation may be sparse, incomplete, or at
times incomprehensible. Although in some cases it may be the case that you need
to cover some background to better understand what you&amp;#8217;re reading, but in most
cases it&amp;#8217;s the documentation you&amp;#8217;re reading which is not perfect. Unfortunately,
it&amp;#8217;s not easy to convince core developers to write good and extensive
documentation, since they&amp;#8217;re mostly busy implementing new features or fixing
reported bugs and&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some packages allow you to suggest an edit to the documentation on the fly, from
the browser itself, which removes the initial barrier for many to start
contributing.
&lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/current/getting-started.html"&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt;
is a good example. As a new user, you probably pay attention to the
documentation probably more than anybody else. Therefore you may find mistakes
or see potential easy improvements which are usually not noticed by other more
experienced users and developers. Be encouraged to suggest any change you deem
appropriate. It may be accepted immediately, or it may start a whole
conversation about a certain aspect of the software. Some of my contributions
have been as small as a punctuation, to make the sentence a bit easier to&amp;nbsp;understand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>How to find a good open source project for contributions?</title><link href="https://adrin.info/how-to-find-a-good-open-source-project-for-contributions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-13:/how-to-find-a-good-open-source-project-for-contributions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Diversity" src="files/img/foss-diversity.jpg" title="Credit: https://blog.mapbox.com/our-code-of-conduct-for-open-source-2b3a81c00c80"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a project to which you&amp;#8217;d like to contribute, there are two
major aspects you may want to consider. One is the way it&amp;#8217;s released and
managed, and the other is the community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see the first aspect, it&amp;#8217;s like a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Diversity" src="files/img/foss-diversity.jpg" title="Credit: https://blog.mapbox.com/our-code-of-conduct-for-open-source-2b3a81c00c80"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a project to which you&amp;#8217;d like to contribute, there are two
major aspects you may want to consider. One is the way it&amp;#8217;s released and
managed, and the other is the community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see the first aspect, it&amp;#8217;s like a spectrum. Closed source proprietary
software on one side (let say the right side), and community driven and fully 
transparent and open
sourced project on the other side (let say the left side).
And it&amp;#8217;s important to realize that different
projects are somewhere on this spectrum, and not necessarily on either of the
two ends; let aside the whole licensing issue which itself complicates matters
by another order of&amp;nbsp;magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes companies &amp;#8220;release&amp;#8221; the source code of a product, or a part of a
product. Microsoft does this pretty often. You can only look at the code; you
can&amp;#8217;t run it, you can&amp;#8217;t use it, and most people won&amp;#8217;t. To me it&amp;#8217;s more like a
public relations thingy. They use it as a tool to gain reputation among the
community. I see such examples as the ones pretty close the right side of the&amp;nbsp;spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going slightly to the left side of the spectrum, there are projects which are
&amp;#8220;released&amp;#8221; as a whole, and they may even include a friendly license letting
you use it under certain conditions. They may even have a GitHub account and
dump the source code there. Some of these projects are released once, and never
maintained further, and some go through periodical releases; but they still
keep the public community mostly in dark about the development of the
new features. They usually also don&amp;#8217;t really welcome contributions from
&amp;#8220;outsiders&amp;#8221;, and that&amp;#8217;s not because they don&amp;#8217;t like contributions; it&amp;#8217;s mostly
due to the fact that they have limited amount of resources and their priorities
are dictated by the products in which these pieces of software are used. I&amp;#8217;m not
a big fan of contributing to these projects since a large part of the
conversation about the project happens within the team inside the company,
and external contributors are treated somewhat like a second order citizens to
these projects. I get the feeling that projects such as
&lt;a href="https://github.com/explosion/spaCy"&gt;spaCy&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tensorflow"&gt;tensorflow&lt;/a&gt; are such projects. They
have an extremely slow response rate on community questions. You do get the
feeling that it&amp;#8217;s a one sided relationship, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; they release a version,
and if you&amp;#8217;re lucky, your concerns may have been addressed in the&amp;nbsp;release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next group of projects are the ones which are considered as a part of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_and_open-source_software"&gt;free and open source software (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FOSS&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;.
This means not only the software is free and open source, but also volunteers
are encouraged to contribute to it and help it be improved. Naturally, if you&amp;#8217;d
like to work on a project as a volunteer, these are good candidates. But even
within this category of projects, not all of them are a friendly place to
contributors. Fortunately, more and more projects are moving towards having
a proper code of conduct ensuring a harassment free environment, and probably
the most high
profile one among the recent ones is the Linux Kernel project, which recently
confronted Linus Trovalds about it and adopted a
&lt;a href="https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux.git/commit/?id=8a104f8b5867c682d994ffa7a74093c54469c11f"&gt;new code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;.
It is important to realize that there&amp;#8217;s no such thing as the open source
community. The reality is that there are different communities around different
projects/topics. People&amp;#8217;s attitudes differ from community to community,
programming language to programming language,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal experience, which admittedly doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily project the
complete picture about any community since it&amp;#8217;s by definition subjective, has
been the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt; community has always been the harshest in my experience (and I know
  I&amp;#8217;m not alone having experienced that). If you ask a question there which
  sounds &lt;em&gt;stupid&lt;/em&gt; to the experts in the field, they probably would crush you by
  asking why you haven&amp;#8217;t read a &amp;#8220;proper&amp;#8221; book on C++. By that they usually
  mean the whole C++ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; community was really unpleasant to interact, to the point it encouraged
  me to switch from R to Python (yeah, that is in fact why I became a python
  coder). After creating and maintaining three packages for R in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; and
  Bioconductor, I was kinda done with it. I need to mention that this was back
  in 2012, and a lot could have changed in these few years. I have no idea how
  the community behaves these days; and I&amp;#8217;d be delighted if I&amp;#8217;m completely wrong
  about the community&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; has always been nice as far as I&amp;#8217;m concerned. It is a language
  which has it&amp;#8217;s
  &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/psf/codeofconduct/"&gt;own code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;. You can
  imagine how that has influenced the whole community around&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few things you can consider when checking on a [&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FOSS&lt;/span&gt;]&amp;nbsp;project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Activity&lt;/strong&gt;: Is the project under active development? When was the last
  release? How often people open issues and contribute to the project? How often
  do main developers respond to those issues? Many projects may seem pretty cool
  at the first glance, but when you dig deeper, they may be dead projects. Sure
  you can try to revive it, but that may require more dedication and time than
  what you have at&amp;nbsp;hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/strong&gt;: The presence of a code of conduct is neither a necessary
  nor a sufficient condition for a healthy atmosphere in a project, but it&amp;#8217;s a
  sign that the core developers do care about the kind of atmosphere around the
  project. Also, the more people care about codes of conducts, the more pressure
  on the projects to adopt&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Contributions&lt;/strong&gt;: For larger projects, you can check how open the
  community is, by checking the repository logs. There are many tools to
  visualize activity on repositories, for instance, you can check the activity
  around tensorflow
  &lt;a href="http://ghv.artzub.com/#repo=tensorflow&amp;amp;climit=100&amp;amp;user=tensorflow"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
  and activity around scikit-learn
  &lt;a href="http://ghv.artzub.com/#repo=scikit-learn&amp;amp;climit=100&amp;amp;user=scikit-learn"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  You can easily notice how tensorflow has a special user called
  &lt;em&gt;tensorflow-gardener&lt;/em&gt;, and you can read about it
  &lt;a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/how-the-tensorflow-team-handles-open-source-support"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  I personally prefer repositories which have a larger set of contributors
  publicly contributing to the ones hiding internal development behind a special&amp;nbsp;user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treating Contributors&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;#8217;s never pleasant to work with a bunch of snobs!
  As a new contributor, you are bound to make many mistakes, or try things the
  way which is not the common way it&amp;#8217;s done in the project you&amp;#8217;re working on.
  This is
  normal and expected as users join a community. It is very important for the
  core developers of that project to know that and treat newcommers nicely
  and encouragingly. You can see if that&amp;#8217;s the case or not, by going through
  some of the issues and pull requests in the project you&amp;#8217;re checking. Just
  take your time and read some of the conversations happening around some of
  the issues to make sure it suits your taste. You can also check the &amp;#8220;closed&amp;#8221;
  issues
  to see how the core developers handle closing&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another post I&amp;#8217;ll talk about ways you can start contributing to a project
of your&amp;nbsp;choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Why would you want to contribute to an open source project?</title><link href="https://adrin.info/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>adrin</name></author><id>tag:adrin.info,2018-10-09:/why-would-you-want-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenSource" src="files/img/open-source-bart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of open source software for a long time. However, up until
recently, I wasn&amp;#8217;t seriously contributing to any specific project; but why
would you want to contribute to an open source project in the first&amp;nbsp;place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few different aspects to be taken into account here, and here I try
to go through some of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the community&lt;/strong&gt; by contributing to the project. This is the one which
   comes to one&amp;#8217;s mind the most. You like a product, or a community around a
   particular software, hence you contribute to that particular software. Doing
   so, you help yourself (if you use the software) and everybody else who uses
   that same&amp;nbsp;product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the larger community&lt;/strong&gt; by advocating and normalizing open source
   contributions. When you contribute to open source projects, you become yet
   another person who does that and it demystifies open source contributions
   for people around you. Many people (if not most) think you need to be a
   proficient programmer for an open source contributions, not realizing many
   contributions are not even in the form of code. If you work in a place where
   you use those projects in your products, it would make you and your
   colleagues realize how much work goes into those projects, and how your 
   company could benefit from spending time improving it as a part of your&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal recognition&lt;/strong&gt; due to those contributions. Although your first
   contributions may be small, they&amp;#8217;ll grow and become more substantial if you
   stay persistent in your contributions. Sooner or later you become a core
   member of the community you work with, and you&amp;#8217;ll be recognized as such.
   Unlike your contributions to the closed source products in whatever company
   you work, the open source contributions are out there and you don&amp;#8217;t ever
   need to prove that you&amp;#8217;ve done them. It becomes a provable part of your
   professional&amp;nbsp;portfolio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free mentors&lt;/strong&gt; while your contribution gets reviewed. This is only true
   for the friendly and nice project communities, and fortunately their number
   is growing. For quite a few years, if not decades, open source communities
   were mostly toxic, but that&amp;#8217;s changing and people are becoming nicer and
   more patient with newcomers. This means you shouldn&amp;#8217;t fear contributing,
   since the core developers of the project would help you go through the
   process and get your contribution up to the standards of the project. This
   also helps you gain experience working in a larger and more diverse team,
   and feel all the perks and challenges that come with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately not many places encourage their employees and colleagues to
have open source contributions, but still, I don&amp;#8217;t know of a place which would
dislike a candidate who has had some contributions which they can see and check.
Maybe half the job offers I get are because of my presence in the open source&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don&amp;#8217;t accept a job offer which involves no open source
contributions, and I always check what contributions the company and their
employees have. At least in Berlin, the scene is changing fast, and it&amp;#8217;s
becoming somewhat embarrassing for companies not to have any open source
product, and many of them are working on improving on this front. This is partly
due to the fact that many developers prefer an open and transparent company,
and open source is just a part of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the end, the more people contribute to these projects, the more pressure
it puts on companies to include themselves in this movement, which benefits
the larger open source software&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll talk about what these contributions mean, and how one could start
contributing in a separate&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-source"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry></feed>